It was the end of October in the mountains in Austria.
كان ذلك في نهاية تشرين الأول في الجبال في النمسا،
I was there on a field trip with my architecture students from Zurich.
كنا في رحلة ميدانية مع طلابي من الهندسة المعمارية من زيورخ.
And when we reached a high valley,
وعندما وصلنا إلى وادٍ مرتفع،
I surprised them with the news that there was no hut
فاجأتهم بإخبارهم عن عدم وجود أي كوخ
or hotel booked for the night.
أو أي فندق محجوز لهذه الليلة.
It was not a mistake.
لم يكن خطأً،
It was totally on purpose.
كان كل ذلك مقصوداً.
The challenge was to build our own shelter with whatever we could find.
كان التحدي هو بناء ملجئهم الخاص بوساطة أي شيء يمكنهم إيجاده.
And we all survived.
ونجونا جميعاً.
It was cold, it was really tough ...
كان الجو بارداً، وكان الوضع عسيراً...
and it was a great learning experience
وكانت تجربة تعليمية عظيمة
to discover that there are a lot of resources given by nature for free,
لنكتشف وجود الكثير من الموارد تعطينا إياها الطبيعة بالمجان
and all that we need is our sensitivity to see them ...
وأن كل ما نحتاجه هو حسّنا لنراها
and our creativity to use them.
وإبداعنا لنستخدمها.
I found myself in a similar situation.
وجدت نفسي في موقف مشابه
When I was an architecture student about 13 years ago,
عندما كنت طالبة معمارية منذ 13 سنة،
I went to Bangladesh to a remote village called Rudrapur
ذهبت إلى قرية نائية في بانجلادش تدعى ردرابور
with the aim to design and build a school as my thesis project.
بهدف تصميم وبناء مدرسة كأطروحة لمشروعي،
I had lived in that village before when I was 19 and a volunteer
لقد عشت في تلك القرية سابقاً ذلك عندما كان عمري 19 سنة ومتطوعة
at Dipshikha, a Bangladeshi NGO for rural development.
في ديبشيخا، منظمة غير حكومية لتطوير الريف.
And what I had learned from them
والذي تعلمته منهم
was that the most sustainable strategy for sustainable development
أنّ أكثر خطة مستدامة للتنمية المستدامة
is to cherish and to use your very own resources and potential,
هو رعاية واستخدام مواردك وقدراتك الخاصة،
and not get dependent on external factors.
وليس الاعتماد على العوامل الخارجية.
And this is what I tried to do with my architecture as well.
وهذا ما حاولت فعله مع طلابي المعماريين.
In terms of suitable building materials for my school,
من ناحية مواد البناء اللازمة لمدرستي
I didn't have to look far.
لم يتوجب عليّ أن أنظر بعيداً
They were right under my feet:
لقد كانت تحت قدمي:
mud, earth, dirt, clay, however you call it ...
وحل أو تراب أو طين سمها ما تريد
and bamboo that was growing all around.
والخيزران الذي كان ينمو حولنا.
Electricity in remote Bangladesh is rare,
الكهرباء نادرة في المناطق النائية من بانجلادش
but we didn't need it.
لكننا لم نحتجها.
We had human energy
كان لدينا القوة البشرية
and the people were happy to have the work.
وكان الناس سعداء لحصولهم على عمل.
Tools were an issue, too,
وكانت الأدوات مشكلة أيضاً،
but we had these guys,
لكن كان لدينا هؤلاء
water buffalos.
جواميس الماء.
We had also tried a bit cows,
جربنا أيضاً بعض الأبقار،
but interestingly, they were too intelligent.
لكن بشكل مشوّق كانوا أذكياء جداً
They were always stepping in the holes of the previous round.
كانوا يدوسون دائماً في حفر الدائرة السابقة
They wouldn't mix the mud, the straw --
لم يخلطوا الوحل والقش...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
the sand, which are the ingredients in the walls.
والرمل، والتي كانت من مكونات الحائط.
And except a small team of consultants
وباستثناء فريق من المستشارين
like my partner for realization, Eike Roswag,
كشريكي في التحقيق آيك روساغ
and my basket-weaver cousin, Emmanuel,
وابن عمي حائك السلال إيمانويل
it was all built by craftsmen from the village.
قام حرفيو القرية ببنائها كاملاً.
And this is the METI school after six months of construction.
وهذه مدرسة METI بعد ستة أشهر من البناء.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
Load-bearing earth walls that really ground the school,
جدران ترابية محمولة أسست المدرسة،
and large bamboo structures that bring the lightness in.
وبنى خيزرانية كبيرة تدخل الضوء.
That's the classroom on the ground floor.
هذا هو الصف في الطابق الأرضي
Attached to it are the caves.
والمغارات متصلة بها،
They're for reading, for snuggling, for solo work,
إنها للقراءة والراحة والعمل الفردي...
for meditation, for playing ...
للتأمل واللعب،
and the classroom on the top.
والصف في الأعلى.
The children all signed with their names in Bengali the doors,
وقّع الأطفال أسماءهم بالبنغالية على الأبواب
and they did not only sign, they also helped building the school.
لم يقوموا بالتوقيع فقط، لقد ساعدوا أيضاً في بناء المدرسة.
And I'm sure you all had your hands in mud or clay before.
وأنا متأكدة من أنكم وضعتم أيديكم في الوحل أو الطين مسبقاً.
It's wonderful to touch. I love it.
إنها رائعة الملمس، أنا أحبها.
The children loved it.
أحبها الأطفال.
And can you imagine the feeling of a small boy or a girl
ويمكنك تخيل شعور طفل أو طفلة صغيرة
or an illiterate day laborer standing in front of that school building
أو عامل يومي أمّي واقفاً أمام بناء المدرسة
and knowing that you built this
عارفاً أنك قد بنيت هذه
out of the ordinary bamboo and just the dirt underneath your feet,
من خيزران طبيعي ومجرد وحل تحت قدمك،
using nothing but your hands?
مستخدماً يديك فقط؟
That gives such an enormous boost of trust and confidence
سيعطي ذلك تعزيزاً هائلاً في المسؤولية
in yourself and the community.
في نفسك والمجتمع.
And in the material.
وفي المواد.
Especially mud has a very poor image.
ويملك الوحل بالأخص صورة ضعيفة المستوى
When we think of mud, we think of dirt --
عندما نفكر في الوحل يتبادر لنا الرمل
it's ugly, it's nondurable --
إنه بشع وغير متين ...
and this is the image I want to change.
وهذه الصورة التي أريد تغييرها.
In fact, it's the 11th rainy season for this school now,
في الواقع، هذا هو الموسم الماطر الحادي عشر لهذه المدرسة
really harsh, horizontal monsoon rains,
أمطار موسمية قاسية
and the walls are standing strong.
وما زالت الجدران صامدة بقوة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So how does it work?
إذاً كيف يعمل كل هذا؟
First rule, a good foundation that keeps the wall dry from the ground,
القاعدة الأولى هي الأساس الجيد الذي يجعل الحائط جافاً من الأرضية،
and second rule, a good roof that protects from the top,
القاعدة الثانية هي السقف الجيد والذي يقوم بالحماية من الأعلى،
and third rule, erosion control.
والقاعدة الثالثة هي التحكم بظروف التعرية.
Mud walls need speed breakers
تحتاج جدران الوحل مشتتات للماء المتدفق
so that the rainwater cannot run down the wall fast,
إذ يمنع ماء المطر من التدفق بسرعة على الحائط،
and these speed breakers could be lines of bamboo
ويمكن أن تكون هذه المشتتات صفوفاً من الخيزران
or stones or straw mixed into the mud,
أو أحجار أو قشاً مخلوطاً بالوحل،
just like a hill needs trees or rocks in order to prevent erosion.
تماماً كاحتياج التلة للأشجار والصخور لمنع التعرية.
It works just the same way.
إنها تعمل بطريقة مشابهة.
And people always ask me if I have to add cement to the mud,
ويسألني الناس دائماً فيما إذا يتوجب علي إضافة الإسمنت للوحل
and the answer is no.
والجواب هو لا.
There is no stabilizer, no coating on these walls,
لا يوجد رواسخ أو أغطية على هذه الجدران
only in the foundation.
الأساسات فقط.
So this is the close-up of the wall
وهذه نظرة قريبة للحائط
after 10 rainy seasons,
بعد عشرة مواسم من المطر.
and as much as I grew a bit older,
وكما كبرت في السن قليلاً
the wall got some wrinkles as well.
ظهر بعض التغصنات على الحائط أيضاً
The edges my not be as sharp as before,
ربما لا تكون الحواف حادة كالسابق
but it still looks pretty good,
لكنها ما زالت تبدو جيدة
and if it needs repairing,
وإذا احتاجت الإصلاح،
it is really easy to do.
فإن من السهل فعل ذلك.
You just take the broken part,
ستقوم فقط بأخذ الجزء المتضرر
make it wet, and put it back on the wall,
تبلله وتعيده إلى الحائط،
and it will look the same as before.
وسيبدو مشابهاً للسابق.
Wish that would work on me, too.
أتمنى أن يعمل ذلك معي أيضاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah, and the great thing is,
والشيء العظيم هو،
if an earth wall is not needed anymore,
إذا لم يعد هناك حاجة لحائط ترابي،
it can go back to the ground it came from,
يمكن إعادته إلى الأرض من حيث أتى
turn into a garden,
يمكن تحويله إلى حديقة،
or get fully recycled without any loss of quality.
أو يتم إعادة تدويره بدون أي خسارة في الجودة.
There's no other material that can do this,
لا يوجد أي مادة يمكنها أن تقوم بهذا
and this is why mud is so excellent in terms of environmental performance.
لهذا فإن الوحل ممتاز في حالة الأداء البيئي.
What about the economic sustainability?
ماذا عن استدامة الاقتصاد؟
When we built the school,
عندما بنينا المدرسة
I practically lived on the construction site,
عشت في موقع البناء تحديداً
and in the evening, I used to go with the workers to the market,
واعتدت أن أذهب مع العمال كل مساء إلى السوق
and I could see how they spent their money.
واستطعت أن أرى كيف صرفوا أموالهم.
And they would buy the vegetables from their neighbors,
كانوا يشترون الخضراوات من جيرانهم،
they would get a new haircut or a new blouse from the tailor.
يحصلون على تسريحة شعر جديدة أو كنزة جديدة من الحائك.
And because the main part of the building budget
ولأن الجزء الرئيس من ميزانية البناء
was spent on craftsmanship,
تم صرفه على الحرفة،
the school wasn't just a building,
لم تكن المدرسة مجرد بناء،
it became a real catalyst for local development,
أصبحت تحفيزاً حقيقياً للتطوير المحلي
and that made me happy.
وهذا جعلني سعيدة.
If I had designed the school in cement and steel,
إذا ما صممت المدرسة باستخدام الإسمنت والمعدن،
this money would have been exported and lost for those families.
كل هذه الأموال ستُصرَف وستخسرها هذه العائلات.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The building budget at that time was 35,000 euros --
كانت ميزانية البناء حينها 35000 يورو
it's probably doubled by now --
وغالباً تضاعفت هذه القيمة الآن...
and this is a lot of money for that region,
وهذا كثير من المال بالنسبة لتلك المنطقة
and especially because this money is working within the community
وبالأخص لأن هذا المال يعمل داخل المجتمع،
and rotating fast,
ويتناوب بسرعة،
and not on the stock market.
ليس في خزينة السوق فقط.
So when it comes to the economic sustainability of my project,
لذا عند الحديث عن الاستدامة الاقتصادية في مشروعي
my main question is, who gets the profit?
سؤالي الرئيس هو من يحصل على الربح؟
How many of you in here
كم شخصاً منكم هنا
have some experience living in a mud house?
جرّب العيش في بيت من الوحل؟
Chris Anderson, where is your hand?
أين يدك كريس أندرسون؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You? OK.
أنت؟ حسناً
Yeah.
أجل
It seems totally out of our focus,
يبدو ذلك خارج إدراكنا تماماً،
but approximately three billion people all around the planet
لكن تقريباً ثلاثة مليار شخص حول الأرض
are living in earth houses,
يعيشون في بيوت ترابية.
and it is a traditional building material
وهو مادة بناء تقليدية
in Europe just as much as in Africa.
في أوروبا كما في إفريقيا.
Strangely enough,
للغرابة،
mud is not considered worthy of being studied at universities ...
لا يعتبر الوحل ذو قيمة لتتم دراسته في الجامعات،
so I brought the dirt to Harvard,
لذلك أحضرت التراب إلى هارفارد،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
precisely 60 tons of dirt right in front of the main facade
60 طن من التراب تحديداً أمام الواجهة الرئيسة
of the Graduate School of Design.
لمدرسة التأهيل في التصميم.
Students and faculty rolled up their sleeves,
استعد الطلاب ومن في الكلية للعمل.
got their hands dirty
وشرعوا في العمل
and transformed the front into a warm place for people to gather.
وحولوا الواجهة إلى مكان دافئ يجتمع فيه الناس.
Children would climb the structures,
يمكن للأطفال أن يتسلقوا الأبنية،
skaters would ride the ramp,
يستطيع المتزلجون التزحلق على المنحدر،
students having lunch breaks,
والطلاب أخذ استراحات الغداء،
and it was particularly fascinating to see how many people were touching the wall,
ومن المدهش تحديداً رؤية عدد الأشخاص الذي كانوا يلمسون الحائط
and we usually don't go around cities caressing our facades, right?
ونحن لا نتجول في المدن عادة ونعانق الواجهات، أليس كذلك؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Of course, this was a small-scale project,
كان هذا المشروع بالطبع صغير المدى
but in terms of awareness-building and in terms of education,
لكن في حالة الوعي البنائي والتعليم
it was like an acupuncture trigger point.
كان هذا كنقطة تحول
And in fact, in more and more countries,
وفي الواقع، في بلدان أكثر وأكثر
load-bearing earthen structures are not allowed to be built anymore
الأبنية المحمولة على التراب غير مسموح بها بعد الآن،
although they're traditional and have lasted for hundreds of years,
على الرغم من كونها تقليدية وصمودها لمئات السنين
and not because the material is weak,
وليس لأن المادة ضعيفة،
but because there are no architects and engineers
لكن بسبب عدم وجود مهندس أو معماري
who know how to deal with that material.
يعلم كيف يتعامل مع هذه المادة.
So education on all levels,
لذا فالتعليم على كافة المستويات،
for craftsmen, engineers and architects,
للحرفيين والمهندسين والمعماريين
is really strongly needed.
مطلوب بشدة.
Equally important is technological development,
والتطوير التقني مهم أيضاً بشكل مشابه،
like prefabrication developed by my colleague Martin Rauch,
كالأبنية مسبقة الصنع التي طورها زميلي مارتن روتش،
who is an Austrian artist and expert in earthen structures.
وهو فنان نمساوي وخبير في الأبنية الترابية
And he has created technologies for rammed earth elements,
وصنع أيضاً تقنيات لعناصر التربة المضغوطة،
for prefabrication of rammed earth elements
للأبنية مسبقة الصنع بطريقة التربة المضغوطة
that include insulation, wall heatings and coolings
وهذا يتضمن عوازل ومبردات ومسخنات الجدران
and all sorts of electrical fittings
وكل أنواع اللوازم الكهربائية،
that can be layered to multistoried buildings,
والتي يمكن أن توضع كطبقات في الأبنية متعددة الطوابق
and this is important in order to scale up
وهذا مهم من أجل رفع
and in order to fasten up the processes,
ومن أجل تسريع العمليات
like in the Ricola Herb Center in Switzerland.
كمركز أعشاب ريكولا في سويسرا.
And finally, we need good built projects
ونحتاج في النهاية إلى مشاريع جيدة
that prove you can build with an ancient material
تثبت أنه بإمكاننا البناء بمواد قديمة
in a very modern way.
بطريقة حديثة جداً
It is not a matter of how old a material is;
ليس من المهم قدم المادة
it's a matter of our creative ability to use it today.
المهم هو قدرتنا على الإبداع في استخدامها اليوم.
These, for example, are three hostels
وعلى سبيل المثال هذه النزلات الثلاثة
that I did in China in the village Baoxi,
التي صممتها في قرية بوشي في الصين
about six hours by bus from Shanghai.
وتبعد عن شنغهاي ست ساعات بالحافلة،
The outside shape is woven bamboo,
يتألف الهيكل الخارجي من الخيزران المحبوك
and the inside core is stones and rammed earth.
والداخلي من الحجار والتراب المضغوط
And it is a traditional building material.
وهو ماد بناء تقليدية.
Even large parts of the Great Wall of China
حتى أجزاء كبيرة من سور الصين العظيم
have been built with rammed earth,
بنيت بالتراب المدكوك،
but it's getting replaced by concrete.
لكن يتم استبدالها بالإسمنت.
And this trend is happening very fast.
وهذه النزعة تحدث بسرعة كبيرة.
Within only a couple of years,
خلال عامين فقط،
China has consumed more cement than the United States
استهلكت الصين إسمنتاً أكثر من الولايات المتحدة
in the entire 20th century.
في القرن العشرين كاملاً.
And this trend of replacing natural building materials
وهذه النزعة إلى استبدال مواد البناء الطبيعية
with materials that require a lot of energy,
بمواد تتطلب الكثير من الطاقة
that are energy-intensive,
والتي تستهلك الطاقة
and that emit CO2
وتبعث ثنائي أوكسيد الكربون
is really clearly contributing to climate change.
تساهم بشكل واضح في التغيّر المناخي
And we have alternatives,
ولدينا بدائل
such as mud, stones, timber, bamboo, earth,
كالوحل والحجارة والأخشاب والخيزران والتراب
that are totally effective options for all sorts of purposes.
والتي تشكل خيارات فعالة لكل الغايات.
This, for example, is an office building that we did
هذا على سبيل المثال مبنى مكتبي صممناه
for Omicron Electronics in Austria.
لإلكترونيات أميكرون في النمسا.
Mud is healthy for the planet, but also for the human bodies,
يعد الوحل صحياً لكوكب الأرض ولأجسام البشر أيضاً
and the material is low-tech,
والمادة منخفضة المستوى
but the performance is high-tech.
لكن الأداء عال المستوى
The earth walls keep the highly sophisticated tools in the building safe
تبقي الأعمدة الترابية الأدوات المتطورة في أمان
by naturally regulating moisture.
عن طريق تنظيم الرطوبة طبيعياً
And this wall in my own home
وهذا الحائط في منزلي
is our humidfier.
هذا هو معدل الرطوبة الخاص بنا.
We love our six tons of dirt at home
نحن نحب الأطنان الستة من التراب في منزلنا
not only because it's healthy and sustainable.
ليس لكونها صحية ومستدامة فقط.
Its archaic warmth is touching deep within.
دفؤها القديم يلمسنا عميقاً.
My personal dream is to build a mud skyscraper right in Manhattan.
حلمي الشخصي هو بناء ناطحة سحاب وحلية في قلب مانهاتن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah.
أجل
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And this dream isn't so crazy
وهذا الحلم ليس مجنوناً
if you think of the mud city of Shibam in Yemen
إذا فكرتم في مدينة شبام الوحلية في اليمن
that was built in the 16th century
والتي بنيت في القرن السادس عشر
and has lasted now for 500 years.
وبقيت 500 عام حتى الآن.
What was possible that long ago is possible today as well,
الذي كان ممكناً منذ وقت طويل ممكن الآن أيضاً
and we can apply all our technical know-how
ويمكننا تطبيق كل معارفنا التقنية
to these ancient materials
لهذه المواد القديمة
so that it meets our needs and our dreams.
حتى نحقق احتياجاتنا وأحلامنا.
All around us,
حولنا،
and just below our feet ...
وتماماً تحت أقدامنا
are wonderful natural building materials.
مواد بنائية طبيعية مذهلة
Let's use them.
دعونا نستخدمها.
And I deeply believe
وأعتقد بقوة
our homes, our work spaces, our cities
أن بيوتنا وأماكن عملنا ومدننا
would become more healthy and sustainable
ستصبح أصح وأكثر استدامة
and more humane
وأكثر إنسانية
and beautiful.
وجمالاً.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)